Finding aid for the Betty Millard papers SSC.MS.00673
Sophia Smith Collection
Betty Millard papers
1911-2010
Sophia Smith Collection
Millard, Betty
SSC.MS.00673
27.31 linear feet (72 boxes and oversize materials)
Betty Millard was a writer, political and labor activist, and photographer. She was involved in Communism and Marxism and was interested in global social justice. Millard was the author of Woman Against Myth, a key feminist seminal that examined the history of the women's movement in the United States, in the socialist movement, and in the USSR. The papers document Millard's personal and professional life. It includes writings by, about, and collected by Millard, paper records of Millard's travels, and personal journals from the entirety of her life, some which document her personal exploration of, and struggle with, her sexuality.
Biographical Note
Elizabeth (Betty) Boynton Millard was born on October 12, 1911. She was born to a wealthy, conservative family in Highland Park, Illinois and lived there until she attended college. Her mother, Elizabeth (Bessie) Bell Boynton (1882-1980) was a Smith College student from 1900-1902 and studied painting, sculpture, and music. She became an artist. Her father, Everett Lee Millard (1877-1933) was an attorney. Betty was the second of four children; younger to Everett Lee (Chevy) Millard, Jr. (1909-2000); older to Malcolm (Mac) S. Millard (1914-1999), and Graham Millard (1921-1921). Malcolm's first wife, Margaret Wentworth Owings, whose work focused on endangered species conservation, was a life-long friend to Betty Millard. Betty Millard remained close to her brother Malcolm throughout her life, despite their significant political and lifestyle differences. Her closest familial relationship for the latter half of her life was with her niece Olivia Millard, with whom she shared a love of nature, travel and conservation.
Millard first attended the University of Chicago from 1930-1932, but transferred to Barnard College in 1932. She briefly studied at the University of London and in Vienna during her college years. Her interest in political activism and social justice flourished during this time period and directed her professional interests for the continuation of her life. Millard was drawn to the on-campus activism at Barnard College, and marched against the U.S. government's support of Francisco Franco in the Spanish Civil War. She graduated from Barnard College in 1934 and enrolled at Columbia Law School, but left after one year in order to pursue her activism. In exploring her preferred ideals of equality and fairness, Betty joined the Young Communist League in 1936 and the Communist party in 1940. In 1935, she moved to Greenwich Village, where she was based for the rest of her life.
From 1943-1947, Betty Millard worked as an editor and writer at The New Masses, a publication focused on American Marxism. In 1947, during her time at The New Masses, Betty wrote the widely acclaimed, key feminist seminal, Woman Against Myth. It was published as a 24-page pamphlet in 1948 distributed with the magazine and was released by International later that year.Woman Against Myth examined the history of the women's movement in the United States, in the socialist movement, and in the USSR.
From 1949-1951, Betty Millard worked in Paris, France and Berlin, Germany as the American Secretary in the directorate of the Women's International Democratic Federation (WIDF). The WIDF was a post-war, radical feminist organization that aligned with the global Communist movement. Millard was also active in the Congress of American Women (CAW), an affiliate of WIDF. Her work for both organizations took her to France, Italy, the Soviet Union, Poland, Hungary, China, Finland, Denmark, Switzerland, and Germany. When she returned to the United States in 1951, her passport was lifted due to suspected Communist affiliation.
From 1951-1956, Betty Millard worked as an editor and writer at the magazine Latin America Today, reporting on the political and social developments south of the United States border. In April 1959, Millard was subpoenaed to testify as a hostile witness before the House of Un-American Activities Committee during the McCarthy trials. The House was investigating the Congress of American Women, Millard's work for them, as well as her personal political views. Millard left the Communist Party in the late 1950's – possibly as a result of the Khrushchev revelations, or possibly out of dissatisfaction with the Party's hostile viewpoints on feminism, women's rights and gay rights.
In 1960, Millard developed a passion for photography and installed a darkroom on the top floor of her Greenwich Village brownstone. Millard studied photography with Paul Caponigro, Lisa Modell, and Ansel Adams. She was interested in photography of nature, political struggles, and portraiture. Millard created "picture stories" while travelling including on trips up the Essequibo and Pomeroon Rivers in then-British Guiana; visiting the artist, David Alfaro Siqueiros, at work in his studio; and to Chile in 1970 to photograph Chilean mural art.
Betty Millard spent the remainder of her life travelling to various parts of the world, often in service of advocacy. Betty Millard supported many activist organizations, especially in Latin America. She worked on campaigns such as organizing a committee to free the Mexican muralist, David Siqueiros, from prison, movements that were against the Vietnam War, environmentalism, and later in her life, she joined the fight for lesbian and gay rights. Millard was also a philanthropist and supported various activist groups, including the North Star Fund, which worked to create a more equitable and democratic city for all New Yorkers. She attended the March on Washington in 1963.
Millard met, interviewed, and befriended a variety of political figures throughout her life including artists David Siqueiros and Diego Rivera, W. E. B. Du Bois, Ho Chi Minh, Zhou Enlai, Fidel Castro, Marie-Claude Vaillant-Couturier, Cheddi and Janet Jagan, Paul and Eslanda Robeson, Elizabeth Moos, and Bella Abzug. Millard and Janet Jagan met while they both attended the University of Chicago. Millard would continue to be close friends with the Jagans for the remainder of their lives.
Millard traveled through British Guiana with politician Cheddi Jagan as he campaigned for Chief Minister, and later, Premier. She spoke alongside Jagan at an event in New York City shortly after he was elected President of independent Guyana on December 5, 1992. In this, her last public speaking appearance, she eloquently compared Jagan's early campaign-trail appeal to that of the recently-elected U.S. President, Bill Clinton.
Despite privately writing about her struggles with her sexual orientation in journals, Millard did not come out as gay until her late 80s except to close family and friends. Millard often referenced her crushes on schoolmates in her journals and described her younger self as bisexual. Due to the social implications of being gay and the explicit homophobia of the Communist Party, Millard took measures to reject this part of her life by seeking conversion therapy from 1942-1948; she was hospitalized in 1956 for a breakdown related to her struggles with her sexuality. Despite this, Millard had several important long-term relationships with women prior to, and after, coming out.
Millard enjoyed writing short stories and poetry, most of which were autobiographical. Some of Millard's writing was anthologized, and others can be found in The Guardian. In 1960, Millard purchased a small farm in Dutchess County, upstate New York and regularly spent time there.
Millard passed away on March 6, 2010 at her home in New York City, New York.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use with following restrictions on access: Some materials are deteriorating and are fragile and require care during use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Betty Millard papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by her estate executors - her niece, Olivia Millard, and her close friend, Lisa Springer, in two accessions in 2011 and 2013. Subsequent additions are not expected.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following collections at Smith College Special Collections:
MS 452, Communism, Socialism, and Left-Wing Politics Collection
MS 594, Women's International Democratic Federation (WIDF) Records
MS 482, Miscellaneous Organizations Collection
Additional WIDF materials can be found in the Sophia Smith Collection in the papers of
MS 300, Mary Metlay Kaufman
MS 85, Dorothy Kenyon
MS 165, Mary van Kleeck
MS 175, Ruth Frances Woodsmall
WIDF's magazine Women of the Whole World is located with the MS 537,Sophia Smith Collection Periodicals Collection
Betty Millard's mother, Elizabeth (Bessie) Bell Boynton (1882-1980) was a Smith College student from 1900-1902 and studied painting, sculpture, and music. Materials can be found within the Smith College Archives.
The Margaret Owings Collection resides at the Bancroft Library.
Scope and Contents
The Betty Millard papers span the period of 1884-2011 and relate to both her personal and professional life. The bulk of the papers span 1915-2011. The major topic of the papers revolve around Millard's professional life and her personal writings. The collection includes clippings, articles, correspondence, personal and collected writings, and audiovisual materials.
Arrangement
The materials are organized into five series:
Biographical
Correspondence
Professional
Writings
Audiovisual
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
As a preservation measure, researchers must use digital reproductions of the audiovisual materials in this collection. Access to audiovisual materials requires the creation of digital access copies. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request digitization of and access to materials.
Millard, Betty; Jagan, Cheddi; Jagan, Janet; Vaillant-Courturier, Marie-Claude; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963; Siqueiros, David Alfaro; Castro, Fidel, 1926-2016; Levit, Herschel; Communists--Biography; Women communists; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities; Congress of American Women; Women and peace; Women's International Democratic Federation; Women journalists--United States--Biography; Latin America--Description and travel; Lesbian activists; Millard, Olivia; Millard, Olivia
- Biographical materials, circa 1884-2010; 1; 5.3 linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  The Biographical Materials series contains biographical information about Millard's personal life. It includes address books, biographies/autobiographies, clippings, journals, memorabilia, and information about her early childhood years and education. The journals are from early to late in her life, are very detailed, and include information on her education (with sketches and class notes), travelling (with maps, journaling, and notes), personal journals, and journals on her gardening (with maps, sketches, and notes). Memorabilia includes United Nations membership cards, passports, and collected buttons. Autobiographies include detailed lists of trips with friends, companions, and various jobs she had.
  - Address books, circa 2003 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Articles and clippings, circa 1921-1999 (Box 1, Folder 4-10)
  - Autobiographies, 1963-2010 (Box 1, Folder 11-13)
  - Biographies, 1997-2012 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Calendars, 1930-2010 (Box 2, Folder 1-8)
  - Financial records, 1978-1999 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Journals, 1925-1996 (Box 3, Folder 2-6)
  - Journals: Garden journal, 1967-1987 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Journals: Travel notebooks, 1949-1998; 19 folders (Box 3, Folder 8-11, Box 4, Folder 1-15)
  - Memorabilia: Buttons, circa 1919-1984; 1-4 folders (Box 5, Folder 1-4, Box 6)
  - Memorabilia: Hair, 1911-1951; 1 folders (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Memorabilia: Lightbox, Undated; 1 folders (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
  - Memorabilia: Matchbooks, Undated; 1 folders (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Memorabilia: Sketches, Undated; 1 folders (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Memorabilia: Stamps, Undated; 1 folders (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
  - Memorabilia: Korea purse, Undated; 1 boxes (Box 8)
  - Memorabilia: Blank travel postcards, Undated; 1 boxes (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous: Jobs and photography, Circa 1966-1970 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1930-1969 (Box 10, Folder 2-3)
  - Miscellaneous: Receipts, 1884-1889 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Notes: Elizabeth Moos, 1984-1985 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Notes: General, circa 1945-2003 (Box 10, Folder 6-8)
  - Notes: Office, circa 1954-1957 (Box 10, Folder 9-10)
  - Notes: Writing and obituaries, circa 1997-1999 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Personal: Birth certificate, 1911 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Personal: Passports, 1931-1995 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Personal: Passport paperwork, 1958 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Personal, 1896-1953 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Personal: Camp Quinibeck, 1925-1930 (Box 11, Folder 1-6)
  - Travel, 1949-1994 (Box 11, Folder 7-11)
  - Educational, circa 1918-1942 (Box 12, Folder 1-15, Box 13, Folder 1-13, Box 14, Folder 1-12)
- Correspondence, circa 1918-2010; 2; 3.13 linear feet
  The Correspondence series is arranged first by subject and then chronologically. Some notable correspondents include Cheddi and Janet Jagan, Marie-Claude Vaillant-Couturier, and W.E.B. Du Bois. There is correspondence from her time at the organizations she worked at. Much of the chronological correspondence contains letters between Millard and her family members. Millard's original subpoena from Congress to testify to the Committee on Un-American Activities on April 21, 1959 is included in the 1951-1959 correspondence.
  - Holiday Cards, 1955-2007 (Box 14, Folder 13, Box 15, Folder 1-5)
  - Letters to family, circa 1918-1982 (Box 16, Folder 1-4, Box 17, Folder 1-3)
  - Julia Allen, circa 2000-2003 (Box 17, Folder 4-6)
  - Carleton Beals, circa 1962-1988 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Personal correspondence and notes, 1958-2000 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Cheddi and Janet Jagan, 1956-1999 (Box 18, Folder 1-3)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1976-1996 (Box 18, Folder 4-5)
  - Marie-Claude Vaillant-Couturier, 1952-1992 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Gita Banerjea, 1950-1987 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - W.E.B. Du Bois, 1955-1959 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Lloyd L. Brown, 1976-1997 (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Earl Robinson, circa 1988-1990 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - North Star Fund, circa 1974-1999 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Latin American Today, circa 1951-1966 (Box 19, Folder 2-3)
  - To Betty Millard at New Masses, 1945-1958 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Latin America correspondence, circa 1953-1954 (Box 19, Folder 5-8)
  - Latin American Research Bureau (LARB) activities, circa 1951-1956 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Regarding Betty Millard's writings, circa 1945-1948 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - 1931-1939 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - 1940-1949 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - 1947-1954 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - 1947-1967 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - 1949-2007 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - 1951-1954 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - 1951-1959 (Box 20, Folder 5-6)
  - 1951-2008 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - 1953 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - February-December 1955 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - 1964-1970 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - 1966-2011 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - 1971-1972 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - 1972-1975 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - 1983-1987 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - 1995-1996 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - 1999-2000 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - 1999-2003 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - 2000-2008 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - 2001-2003 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - circa 2002-2003 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - 2002-2006 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - 2010 (Box 22, Folder 7)
- Professional records, circa 1931-1996; 3; 2.96 linear feet
  The Professional Records series is organized into three categories: Administrative, Subjects, and Research. Notable folders include Millard's activist work in the Artists Committee for Siqueiros organization, research for her writings, transcript and notes from her interview with Diego Rivera, and copies of newsletters and pamphlets from various news outlets and organizations she worked for.
  - Administrative: Floppy disks, circa 1985-1997 (Box 23)
  - Administrative: MCM Art Prism, Undated (Box 23)
  - Administrative: Letterheads, Undated (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Subjects: Artists Committee for Siqueiros, 1959-2001 (Box 24, Folder 2, Box 25, Folder 1-5, Box 26, Folder 1-6)
  - Subjects: Diego Rivera interview, circa 1954-1955, 7 folders (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - Subjects: Marie Claude Vaillant-Couturier, 1955-1996; 2 Cassettes (Box 26, Folder 8-9, Box 27, Folder 1-2)
  - Subjects: Cheddi and Janet Jagan, circa, 1977-1992; 1 folders (1-2) (Box 28, Folder 1-2)
  - Research, circa, 1949-1951; 1 folders (3) (Box 28, Folder 3)
  - Research: American Women for Peace (AWP), circa, 1949-1952; 1 folders (4) (Box 28, Folder 4)
  - Research: U.S. Institute on Women, 1949; 1 folders (5) (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Research: Budapest, Second Women's International Congress, 1949; 1 folders (6) (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - Research: VI, Soviet Union (S.U.), undated; 1 folders (7) (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - Research: VII, Other Countries, undated; 1 folders (8) (Box 28, Folder 8)
  - Research: Around the world, circa, 1948-1951; 1 folders (9) (Box 28, Folder 9)
  - Research: Miscellaneous-Women, circa, 1948-1949; 1 folders (10) (Box 28, Folder 10)
  - Research: Congress of American Women (CAW)-Statue of Women Commission (St of W C), circa, 1948; 1 folders (11) (Box 28, Folder 11)
  - Research: Congress of American Women (CAW)-General, circa, 1946-1949; 1 folders (12) (Box 28, Folder 12)
  - Research: United Nations, circa, 1949-1951; 1 folders (13) (Box 28, Folder 13)
  - Research: VIII, Women in Society, circa 1948; 1 folders (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Research: IX, 1947-1948; 1 folders (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Research: X, Women in Society, circa 1948; 1 folders (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Research, circa 1947-1984; 1 folders (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Research: Class, general, circa 1948; 1 folders (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - Research: II, Woman in Society, undated; 1 folders (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - Research: Old Congress of American Women (CAW) writing, 1970-1999; 1 folders (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - Research: Women, Wide - articles, etc. by Betty Millard, circa 1948-1951; 1 folders (Box 29, Folder 8)
  - Research: Charles St. for Peace Organizing, circa 1967-1968; 1 folders (Box 29, Folder 9)
  - Research: Organizing, circa 1931-1936; 1 folders (Box 29, Folder 10)
  - Research: FWI + FG, Fr. in Amer. - Gene, 1964-1966; 1 folders (Box 29, Folder 11)
  - Research: FWI + FG, FG, 1964; 1 folders (Box 29, Folder 12)
  - Research: Guyana, circa 1997-1998; 1 folders (Box 29, Folder 13)
  - Research: Millard's friends and interests, organizing, circa 1979-1990; 1 folders (Box 29, Folder 14)
  - Research: Employment, circa 1959-1961; 1 folders (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Research: Latin American Facts, 1950-1952; 1 folders (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Research: Latin America Today, 1953-1956; 1 folders (Box 30, Folder 3-6)
  - Research: Ideas for Latin America articles, 1957; 1 folders (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - Research: Latin America lists, 1955-1956; 1 folders (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - Research: Latin America testimonials, 1955-1956; 1 folders (Box 30, Folder 9-10)
- Writings, circa 1933-2000; 4; 4.84 linear feet
  The Writings series is organized into two categories: writings by Millard and collected. Millard's writings include drafts and final copies of her pamphlet Women Against Myth, released in 1948 while employed at the publication New Masses; Women On Guard, released in 1948, poetry, short stories, and fiction. Millard's collected writings span the years of 1935-2000.
  There is an incomplete list of slides, negatives, and collected writings and periodicals available.
  - Writing by Millard, 1933-1996; 3 boxes (Box 31, Folder 1-11, Box 32, Folder 1-17, Box 33, Folder 1-13)
  - Collected by Millard, 1935-2000; 11 boxes (Box 33, Folder 14-17, Box 34, Folder 1-19, Box 35, Folder 1-16, Box 36, Folder 1-21, Box 37, Folder 1-17, Box 38, Box 39, Box 40, Folder 1-13, Box 41, Folder 1-14, Box 42, Folder 1-18, Box 43, Box 1)
- Audiovisual materials, circa 1924-1992; 5; 10.88 linear feet
  The Audiovisual Materials series is arranged into four categories: Negatives, Slides, Photographs, and Photograms. There is an incomplete list of slides, negatives, and collected writings and periodicals available.
  - Negatives, circa 1954-1966; 8 boxes (Box 44, Folder 1-11, Box 45, Folder 1-7, Box 46, Box 47, Folder 1-8, Box 48, Folder 1-21, Box 49, Folder 1-54, Box 50, Folder 1-47, Box 51, Folder 1-12)
  - Slides, circa 1963-1992; 9 boxes (Box 51, Folder 13-28, Box 52, Folder 1-26, Box 53, Folder 1-30, Box 54, Folder 1-23, Box 55, Folder 1-22, Box 56, Folder 1-25, Box 57, Folder 1-21, Box 58, Folder 1-17, Box 59)
  - Photographs, circa 1924-2000; 12 boxes (Box 60, Folder 1-15, Box 61, Folder 1-22, Box 62, Folder 1-11, Box 63, Folder 1-16, Box 64, Folder 1-9, Box 65, Folder 1-12, Box 66, Box 67, Folder 1-19, Box 68, Folder 1-5, Box 69, Folder 1-4, Box 70, Box 71, Folder 1-8)
  - Photograms, undated; 1 folders (Box 72, Folder 1)